The next group of operators to look at sequencing
for is the logical group of operators.
Within this group, there is an order of operations
we need to make sure we understand.
I will cover that part first, and then we
will slot this group of operators against
the two types we have already covered: assignment
and comparison.
I have a code example in this 133-logical
file for a logical game situation where one
needs to unlock a level and make a target
score to get a message that a goal has been
met.
There are three logical keywords in use in
Python: not, and, and or.
Take a look at the if statement on line 4.
We will cover if statements elsewhere in the
course but focus on the logical keywords here.
If they have not unlocked a level or their
score is less than the target score, they
will see a message that they still have goals
to make.
Otherwise, they will see that the goals are
met.
In order of operations, not always comes before
and.
And comes before or.
Why is that important?
Think of it this way.
We need to know whether a condition is not
something before we can compare it with other
conditions.
In this context, we have to know if they unlocked
a level before we can compare it to the condition
of the score.
For the test variables on lines 1 and 2, we
see that they unlocked a level, but the score
is less than the target score, so the goals
have not been met.
When we run this code, that’s the message
we get.
To see the importance of not, I will reverse
the criteria in the if statement.
Upon rerunning the code, we get the same result.
Not takes precedence because it only needs
to look at one value and deem it true or false.
A logical keyword such as and or or needs
two values to compare.
In the order of operator precedence, comparison
comes before logical, and logical comes before
assignment since assignment is last in the
order of preferences and not any part of any
comparison or logical statement.